Finding Aid for Douglas Fulton papers, 1950-1999
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Douglas Fulton papers 1950-1999
Fulton, Douglas.
(in 15 boxes)
13.3 linear feet
2008089 Aa 2
Outdoor writer and photographer for The Ann Arbor News, advocate of environment issues, author of local interest and music review columns; articles written and photographs taken by Fulton, personal correspondence and documentation of awards received.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were donated in 2008 by Anna Summers Fulton (donor number 8576 ). The bulk of the materials came to the library in 2008; with additional accession in 2013. Previous materials were received in 1997 and 1999.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Douglas Fulton (1928-1996) was an award-winning outdoor writer and photographer for The Ann Arbor News. He was also a well-known conservationist who worked with various state and local committees, advisory boards, and advocacy groups.
Fulton was born in Illinois and raised in Arizona. He earned a B.A. in languages from the University of Arizona in 1949 and his M.A. in linguistics from the University of Michigan in 1951. Fulton began his career as a photographer with the Air Force; he served for four years in the early 1950s during the Korean War. He was first hired by The Ann Arbor News as a temporary photographer in the late 1950s. He found that he liked journalism and remained with the paper for the duration of his career. In1962, he began writing "A Naturalist's Journal," a weekly column which lasted until his retirement in 1983. In 1968, he was appointed Outdoor Editor and in the following years he expanded the length and scope of this section of the paper. He also wrote a music column for about five years during the 1970s. Due to health problems, Fulton retired early in 1983. He received many awards throughout his career for both his writing and photography. Among those organizations that honored him were the Associated Press, National Press Photographers Association, Outdoor Writers Association of America, and Michigan Outdoor Writers Association.
In his personal life, Fulton worked in various capacities to advocate for the environment. He participated in efforts to create and protect local and state park lands and encouraged low-impact development and helped promote environmental education. Locally, he worked to protect natural areas such as Gallup Park. On the state level, he was instrumental in establishing federal protection for natural areas such as Pictured Rocks National Lakeshore and Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore. He also helped to author the Michigan Wilderness Act. The most notable recognition for his advocacy efforts may have been the Conservation Communicator of the Year award which he received from the Michigan United Conservation Clubs in 1970.
This collection documents Doug Fulton's career as a journalist and photographer for The Ann Arbor News. Personal correspondence and clippings are also included. The collection is divided into four series: Articles, Personal, Visual Materials, and Subject Files.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor news.; Conservation of natural resources--Michigan.; Environmentalism--Michigan.; Fulton, Douglas.; Journalism, Outdoor.; Michigan--Environmental conditions.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Fulton, Douglas.; Ottawa Natural Forest (Mich.); Upper Peninsula (Mich.); Blues music.; Children playing--Michigan.; Conservation of natural resources--Michigan.; Dance.; Plants--Michigan.; Playgrounds--Michigan.; Recreation--Michigan.; State parks & reserves--Michigan.; Theatrical productions--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Trees--Michigan.
Genre Terms:
Black-and-white negatives.; Photographs.
- Articles 1960-1983
  The Articles series (6 linear feet) consists of various articles and photographic pieces that Fulton produced for The Ann Arbor News. These articles feature Fulton's work for several different sections of the paper including Connection (a local interest section), the Outdoor Pages, live music and record review columns, and the Photo Pages of the paper. The bulk of Fulton's work was for the Outdoor and Photo Pages. His work on the Outdoor Pages had a national scope and included purely recreational stories as well as those strongly motivated by his conservationist views. His work on the Photo Pages also covered a wide range of topics. A set of correspondence related to Fulton's work is also included in this series; a significant amount of letters in praise of Fulton's articles and photographs are included here.
  - The Ann Arbor News
    - Connection
      - Bug Camp 1982 (Box 1)
      - Fireworks 1982 (Box 1)
      - Mosquitoes 1982 (Box 1)
      - Poison Ivy 1982 (Box 1)
      - U.S. Secretary of the Interior, James Watt 1982 (Box 1)
      - Solar Access 1982 (Box 1)
      - Various (Box 1)
      - Wildlife Artists 1983 (Box 1)
      - Woodcock 1982 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence
      - Letters of Praise, 3 folders (Box 1)
      - "Record Review" Discontinued (Box 1)
      - Rock Article ("How about starting a 'rock-moving' drive? Here's $50 to open" The Ann Arbor News, November 7, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Drafts and Edits (Box 1)
    - Graphics and Logos (Box 1)
    - Letters to the Editor
      - General (Box 1)
      - From Herman B. (Box 1)
    - "Live Music" Column (Box 1)
    - Outdoor Pages
      - 1968 (Box 1)
      - 1969, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1970, 3 folders (Box 1)
      - 1971, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - 1972, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - 1973, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - 1974, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - 1975, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - 1976, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - 1977, 3 folders (Box 3)
      - 1978, 3 folders (Box 3)
      - 1979, 3 folders (Box 3)
      - 1980, 3 folders (Box 3)
      - 1981, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - 1982, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - 1983 (last article before retirement) (Box 4)
    - Photo Pages
      - 1968-1969, 4 folders (Box 4)
      - 1970-1972, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - 1981, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - 1982 (Box 4)
    - Playgrounds
      - Article Text November 15, 1970 (Box 5)
      - Notes and Drafts (Box 5)
      - Photographs (Box 5)
        (see also oversize folder in box 11)
      - Research, 2 folders (Box 5)
        (includes "Analysis for Play" report containing Fulton photographs)
    - Record Review
      - 1970s (Box 5)
      - 1973, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - 1974 (Box 5)
      - 1975, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - 1976 (Box 5)
      - 1977, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - 1978, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Various
      - 1960s-1980s, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - 1961-1967, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - 1968-1969 (Box 6)
      - 1970s (Box 6)
      - 1980 (Box 6)
      - 1981, 3 folders (Box 6)
      - 1982, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - 1983 (Box 6)
      - Dam Bond 1970 (Box 6)
      - Huron River 1967 (Box 6)
  - Various Publications
    - 1960-1965 (Box 6)
    - 1970s (Box 6)
    - 1985 (Box 6)
    - Travel circa 1968 (Box 6)
    - Washtenaw Wildflowers 1961 (Box 6)
  - Authored by Others
    - The Ann Arbor News Township Series 1956 (Box 6)
- Personal
  The Personal (2 linear feet) series includes coverage of the journalism and conservation awards that Fulton received throughout his career. Also included, is correspondence relating to environmental issues and other personal pursuits.
  - Awards
    - General (Box 7)
    - Writing (Box 7)
  - Biographies (Box 7)
  - Clippings
    - About Fulton (Box 7)
    - General (Box 7)
  - Correspondence
    - 1960s-1980s, 6 folders (Box 7)
    - circa 1990s, 4 folders (Box 7)
    - Employment (Box 8)
    - Letters from Columnists (Box 8)
    - Letters from Fulton (Box 8)
    - Letters to Fulton (Box 8)
    - Letter to President Reagan Regarding Doug Fulton (Box 8)
    - Photograph Researchers, Inc. (Box 8)
    - Undated (Box 8)
  - Curriculum Vitae and Resumes (Box 8)
  - Dedications (Box 8)
  - A Desert Scrapbook (newsletter authored by Doug and Anna Fulton) (Box 8)
  - Employment
    - The Ann Arbor News (Box 8)
    - Tucson Botanical Gardens
      - Interest in Directorship (Box 8)
    - United States Air Force (USAF) (Box 8)
  - Identification Cards (Box 8)
  - Letters to Editor (by Fulton) (Box 8)
  - Local Issues
    - Environmental Education (Box 8)
    - Huron River and Washtenaw County (Box 8)
    - Mayor's Natural Resource Committee (Box 8)
    - Various (Box 8)
  - Obituaries (Box 8)
  - Photographs and Portraits of Doug Fulton (Box 8)
  - Professional Associations
    - Conference Programs (Box 8)
    - Historical Publications (Box 8)
    - Michigan Outdoor Writers Association (MOWA) (Box 8)
    - Outdoor Writers Association of America (OWAA) (Box 8)
  - Speeches and Talks (Box 8)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials (2 linear feet) series includes photographic prints and negatives associated with the stories Fulton worked on throughout his career. As mentioned above, these covered a range of subjects including recreational and conservationist topics, local and national subjects. Also included here are photographs Fulton did for advertisements. Negatives on the subject of nature include aerial images, images of plants, animals, recreational activities, and images taken by Fulton during his trips around Michigan, the U.S. and Canada. Some negatives in this subject group are accompanied by newspaper articles in which images have appeared. The Dance and Theater negatives include images of performances and concerts, mostly dance. Of note are images of Merce Cunningham, Gertrude Prokosch Kurath, José Limón, Louis Mekush, and Elizabeth Weil Bergmann. Also included here is a group of negatives titled Blues Photo Collection with images (and some photographs) of blues musicians. Most of the images in this group were taken during the Ann Arbor Blues and Jazz Festivals
  - Photographs
    - For Advertisements (Box 9)
    - Algonquin Park (Box 9)
    - Ann Arbor Trees (Box 9)
    - Blue Ridge Mountains (Box 9)
    - Bruce Trail (Box 9)
    - Butterflies and Caterpillars (Box 9)
    - Forests (Box 9)
    - Hawks Mountain (West Virginia) (Box 9)
    - Locks, Dams, and Bridges (Box 9)
    - Maple Sugar (Box 9)
    - Osborn Reserve (Box 9)
    - Pictured Rocks (Box 9)
    - Pine River (Box 9)
    - Shakers (Box 9)
    - Shenandoah National Park and Skyline Drive (Box 9)
    - Sonora Desert Museum (Arizona) (Box 9)
    - Sports (Box 9)
    - Sylvania Tract (Ottawa National Forest) (Box 9)
    - University of Virginia (Charlottesville, Virginia) (Box 9)
    - Various
      - 1950s-1960s, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - General, 4 folders (Box 9)
    - Williamsburg (Box 9)
  - Photographs and clippings of photographs (and accompanying articles) which were winners or nominated for various awards for photojournalism; also photos of playgrounds under construction, children at play, children learning about the environment, and photos of outdoor life in general (Box 11)
  - Photographs and clippings of photographs (and accompanying articles) which were winners or nominated for various awards for photojournalism; also photos of playgrounds under construction, children at play, children learning about the environment, and photos of outdoor life in general (Box 12)
    (continued)
  - Negatives
    - Dance and theater
      - Alvin Ailey Dance Troupe (Box 13)
      - Ann Arbor Civic Symphony (Box 13)
      - Ann Arbor Dance Theater (Box 13)
      - Art (Box 13)
      - Association of Producing Artists (Box 13)
      - Canterbury dance (Box 13)
      - Cunningham, Merce (Box 13)
      - Dance, miscellaneous (Box 13)
      - Dance concerts (Box 13)
      - Dance rehearsals (Box 13)
      - German Park (Box 13)
      - Jr. Theater (Box 13)
      - Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch (Box 13)
      - Limón, José (Box 13)
      - Mekush, Louis (Box 13)
      - Plattler kids (Box 13)
      - Scottish dancer (Box 13)
      - Stamps, Phil (Box 13)
      - Taya (Box 13)
      - University of Michigan (Box 13)
      - Weil, Elizabeth (Box 13)
      - West Side Story (Box 13)
      - Untitled negatives (Box 13)
    - Nature
      - Aerial (Box 13)
      - Activities and Recreation (Box 13)
      - Animals (Box 13)
        (includes 3 color slides)
      - Flowers and ferns (Box 13)
      - Forest fire (Box 13)
      - Maps (Box 13)
      - Scenic views (Box 13)
      - Silent Springs Review article (Box 13)
      - Trees (Box 13)
        (includes 1 color slide)
      - Vehicles (Box 13)
      - Washtenaw's wildlands (Box 13)
      - Waterways (Box 13)
      - Weather (Box 13)
  - Negatives with images of nature and outdoors, recreation activities, Fulton' s trips around Michigan, the United States and Canada (Box 14)
    - 1958-1968 (Box 14)
    - 1969-1974 (Box 14)
    - 1975-1982 undated (Box 14)
    - Blues Photo Collection (Box 15)
      - Inventory (Box 15)
      - Ann Arbor Blues Festival 1969 and concerts, 1970-1971 (Box 15)
      - Ann Arbor Blues and Jazz Festival 1972 (Box 15)
      - Blues photographs 1971-1977 (Box 15)
        (includes photographs)
      - Tucson blues 1983-1996 (Box 15)
- Subject Files
  The Subject Files (1 linear foot) series consists of material that Fulton amassed for research purposes. Anti-hunt opinions receive significant coverage and some local issues are also documented. Other wildlife writers and artists, including Bil Gilbert, are also documented within this series.
  - Anti-hunting, 4 folders (Box 10)
  - Barton Boat Launch (Box 10)
  - Brighton Sewage (Box 10)
  - Dean, Elizabeth (environmental benefactor) (Box 10)
  - Eber White Woods (Box 10)
  - ENACT Teach-in (Box 10)
  - Guns, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Harlequin Duck (Box 10)
  - House Bill 4881 (Box 10)
  - Hunting Photography (Box 10)
  - Huron River Development (Box 10)
  - Indians of Baraga Bay (Box 10)
  - Kitt Peak (Tucson, Arizona) (Box 10)
  - Laws (colloquial) and Horoscopes (Box 10)
  - Maple Sugar (Box 10)
  - Olmsted, Frederick Law Sr. (Box 10)
  - Outdoor Writers
    - Bil Gilbert (Box 10)
    - General (Box 10)
  - Porcupine Mountains State Park (Box 10)
  - Railroad Development (Box 10)
  - School Policy on Site Planning and Environmental Education (Box 10)
  - Shakers (Kentucky) (Box 10)
  - Slavic-Kuebler Rezoning Request (Box 10)
  - Soil Conservation Service (Ann Arbor, Michigan) (Box 10)
  - Various (Box 10)
  - Wildlife Art and Artists (Box 10)
  - Woodstoves (Box 10)